Next
Let's start from here
In this chapter we
I talked about it in this chapter.
The most important thing is to talk about the optimization of Datapath
Then we can roughly divide it into two parts.
Today we must at least finish talking about resource optimization
That means I want to optimize today
Datapath optimization
Then let’s review what your design needs to be like
Control path and datapath
That is, Controller and datapath
Then your Controller
Because he has a standard way of writing it, which is 2C1S
You just need to base it on your actual topic
Draw what you call a state diagram
You can follow
follow the two combination circuits
Register and finish writing your Controller
That's because he has a standard way of writing
The datapath is different
Datapath we already talked about last time
He has no standard way of writing
What if your datapath needs to be optimized?
You can look at it from two directions
Of course we know the first one
What are probably the two most important things about all hardware?
The first is cost optimization
The lower the cost, the better
The second one is that the faster the speed, the faster
So the first resource optimization
It’s about cost optimization
The resources here are about hardware.
haadware's resource
It’s about your hardware components
Then we have four ways to do it
Hardware cost optimization
The second one is the optimization of timing.
I wish I ran
The faster my circuit runs, the faster it becomes
At that time, we also have four people here to optimize the time.
That
Last time we actually came to a slightly different conclusion
Reminder
This optimization is basically timing optimizaton
Maybe you don't do much
Because sometimes you want to let
Your circuit is fast enough
You must do timing
Optimization of timing
But resource optimizaton is usually not very good at doing it.
Because once Resource optimizaton is done,
Your circuit must be designed at the gate level.
You can't go too point-to-point
Write it as your circuit
We'll give an example in a moment
You will know by giving an example
This seems not very convenient
Because as long as you use resources
optimizaton Once these methods are used,
Your circuit must be at the gate level
But
In fact, these resource optimization
There is another place
Because it saves some hardware costs
So academically
I can only say that he is quite interesting academically.
Contribute to academics
All academic contributions
That is to say, you designed a circuit
Do something
Then I can do the same thing as you today
But my hardware cost is a little less
I'm missing you by two additions
I'm missing a few of your temporary registers
This is a very good paper
Because my cost is indeed lower than yours
So he will contribute academically
Academically, they won't care if you use gate level.
Or you want to use other methods
But in actual operations, you are in the company
In order to save these two temporary registers,
Then you put your circuit on the gate level
Whether it is debugging
Or that you are writing
It will take a very long time
Maybe it's not necessary
But we will still talk about him
We are going to talk about resource optimization
Personally I don’t think it’s that important
But it allows you to get started
It is important to get started
but you actually
It may not be that important for you to go to the company
That is timing optimization.
This is something you must consider
Because when you go to work in a company
You will have to do timing optimization
Because only timing optimization can
increase your speed
What's next?
The next thing I want to mention is what we talked about last time.
What are these 8 things and 8 optimizations?
We will use an example to string together
Then the example we use is
SRA optimization
so-called square root
optimization means
Suppose I want to calculate the square root today
That’s square root a squared plus b squared
The root of a square plus b square is
I want to calculate this
Follow him a square plus b square
So how do I calculate it?
I want to make a circuit
You are not writing a program now
Instead, you need to make a circuit to achieve this
This and this action
a square plus b square root
Then we mentioned last time that there is a mathematical addition
He wanted an approximate formula
So you can see he is close
Root a squared plus b squared
It can be approximated as this
You can use this formula to approximate
Then this formula is 0.875X
Add 0.5Y
The result of adding these two
This is 0.875X plus 0.5Y
Then there is another x
The greatest value among these two people
So what is x y
x y are respectively a
The absolute value is your input
The larger absolute value of a and b is x
The smaller of the absolute values ​​of a and b is y
Then you bring it into this formula
You can calculate
he got the result
The result is that it is close to the root
a squared plus b squared
Then this is us
What someone here brought up, what about us, what about us?
We have to calculate a squared plus b squared
It becomes to calculate the formula on the right side
So what we have to calculate now is 0.875x
Add 0.5y
Then we have to calculate x
Then what is the maximum value among the two people?
Please ask for one of the two more people.
Relatively large
Then we will start next
Then we have 8 actions to do
The first thing we need to do is storage Sharing
What is storage sharing?
Sharing of storage is the sharing of storage units
So what first?
Let’s look at the word Sharing
Sharing is shared
What about this sharing?
He is actually with that
Usually we are talking about you
If you are in the United States and you want to rent an apartment
I will share it with Dajia
Then there is a problem with this Sharing
His problem is that he is like us
Unlike if you were in Taiwan
When you rent a house in Tainan, there are roughly two categories:
The first is a single suite
Your suite has a room and a toilet
So you don’t have to share the toilet with others.
No Sharing
If you are going with a few classmates
Rented a floor outside
like an apartment
Just three or four rooms
Or it doesn’t matter if it’s Toten
There is only one or two toilets inside
The problem will come at this time
what problem
Sharing
That is to say, this toilet is shared by Dajia.
Maybe three classmates share a toilet
In other words, when classmate a goes to the toilet,
Classmate B can’t attend
Classmate C can’t attend either
Only one person can come in at a time
Same for your living room
Or maybe your kitchen is also shared?
It's basically shared by everyone.
Then the sharing of this storage unit
What is storage unit sharing?
Prioritizing one matter
This only needs to be shared
There will be a problem
I can't use it when you use it. You can't use it when you use it.
Because we share
Then basically you also know the toilet
If you do it, no one else can do it.
If I go, you can't go
So what we are talking about is the Sharing of storage.
The first concept is to be used by others
You can't use
That's the same reason
What does it mean that my storage unit is being used by others today?
It can't be used.
For example, I now have a storage unit
Then I have three classmates here
want to share this storage unit
Then if my storage unit is in addition to
I saved something belonging to classmate A
Then classmates B and C cannot use it.
Because if classmate B also wants to use it
Then store his things in again
Then classmate B will overshadow classmate A.
Because you are sharing storage
What does sharing mean?
I only have one space today
That was used by classmate a
Student B can’t use it. Student B uses it.
Classmate A’s information disappeared
So this storage unit is shared
only occurs in those data
A situation that can be covered up means that
Otherwise because it is shared
So let's take a look
What about Sharing of this storage?
For example, let's look at this mathematical formula
What if my...
Think of it like I have a software
The program needs to be calculated
x=a+1
I want to put the result of a+1 into x
So here's what I'm going to do up there.
Then wait, wait, wait, I'm going to keep doing this
After doing this, I have to calculate y=c+d
I want to c+d
The result is placed in y
Then this is what you need to do in these two states.
You can see this on the left
That's the normal situation
I need a scratchpad
I want to save x
Because the result of a+b needs to be stored in x
So I need a storage space
Then this storage space is what we talked about earlier.
register you may want to have a 32 bit register
Or a 64-bit register to store x
Then you also need a register
Come and save y
Because you want to put the result of a plus b into x
Put the result of c plus d into y
So you x need a scratchpad
Then you also need a temporary register
Then if you didn’t do any shrinking at all
Just like the picture in the middle means
Because there is an addition at the bottom
So this is where it starts
selector
Multiplexer
The selector goes here to select a
Then select b here
He has an adding machine here
He will help you do a plus b
result of addition
You save it to x
Then you can finish this thing
x=a+b
Wait until you pass a few states
Next you need to do c plus d
If you put it in y, you will select c on the selector side.
Select d here in the selector
Then after this addition is completed,
The result is saved to y
c+d is stored in y
So you actually used two
One storage unit stores x and the other stores y.
It can be seen
You have two storage units
A deposit x
A deposit
This is not shared
Then take a look
Let’s take another look at our topic:
Storage sharing is sharing
When can it be shared?
The point is right
This is also very important
Because I just mentioned the topic earlier
So sharing means that I can’t use it when you use it.
Can't you use it when I use it?
Right? Then what?
We x,y
Can I share a storage space?
I only have one storage space
You wanted two originally
Then we will use a storage space to store x
Save y again
When can I save x?
Can I save y?
Here is his premise
If you say you look at you you
Imagine I add a plus b
Then calculate x
Then this x
I need a storage space
Then I have a program
What if x
The value is used up
No one will use x again in the future
Is it right? I can put y
Also save to the space on x
But his premise is
Because if someone else uses yours, it will disappear.
So this concept of sharing means
If you use it, I can't use it anymore
Then my storage space assumes that I save my value
Then one day I will tell you
You can also exist here
As soon as you deposit it, my value will disappear.
So if you calculate x here
What about when you're in this state?
Several more states passed below
x will not be used again at this time
I can save the result of c+d in
I can use the same space for this y
This is called register sharing
so
When is the only time he can do this?
The life of x and y
What is life span
That means I have to figure it out x
I x want to always remember
right?
But I may always use x here
That's okay, I always remember x
I can use it when I think of it.
But when I want to produce y today
To save the past time
Assume that I will never use x again later
I can put x
Release this temporary storage space
Come and save y
Because the life spans of two people do not overlap
no overlap
So this is called temporary register sharing.
So what do we do?
In fact, take this example
It will come faster than the half-day meeting I just had.
Give you 30 seconds
You first need to convert the root number of the one just now
Let’s look at the example again, okay?
let's take a look
One is the root of a squared plus b squared
Then we have just
I'll help you review again. You just calculate 0.875x
Add 0.5Y
And x
Find the largest among two people
What about your XY?
If you calculate AB separately, the one with the larger absolute value is x.
If AB each finds the smaller absolute value, it is y.
This is our previous understanding
Then take a look at it again
When designing your circuit, you should separate controllers.
With datapath
We won’t talk about the controller anymore.
Because the controller is after you draw the set
2C1S
But you need to have experience to bring him datapath.
How do you want to design
will be a complete datapath
So what we are talking about now is the datapath part
Then if you want to consider Register Sharing
Then let's see if you want to do 1234
Then when checking these four steps
Let’s go through this process again first
At first you have to read it in and put it into a
The first input is read as a
The second one reads b
Because you have to calculate the square root of a square plus b square
right?
You need to calculate the square root of a square plus b square.
So why do you want to
Let's say you have two inputs
Then you read the first input and put it into a
The second input is read in and placed in b
Next I sent a start signal
It means I'm going to start doing it
Then what will I ask for first when I start doing it?
The absolute value of a and the absolute value of b
Suppose I perform an action in a state
So now I have read in all the values ​​of a and b.
So I put the absolute value of a into t1
The absolute value of b is placed in t2
Because I have to calculate this first
The absolute value of a The absolute value of b
Here we have to go with the front pocket
This matter is in your current state
you do two things
These two actions are done simultaneously
Then let me ask Dajia
Can you say I will do t1 first and then t2?
It can be divided into two states.
You want a state to count t1 at the same time
It can also count t2 at the same time.
This is what it means here
I calculate t1 at the same time in this state
Count t2 at the same time
Then what can I do?
I can also divide it into two states
The first state is counted as t1
The second state is counted as t2
So you need one state or two states here
It's your plan
What you planned is different
Your entire circuit will be different.
So what is his cost?
You want you to go and you have to think about this.
Because we have been teaching the whole time
This is what you want
For example, if you look at
When you write your status like this
Count t1 at the same time
Count t2 at the same time
right?
That means you want some hardware that is absolutely worth it.
You have to have two at the same time
Because when you do the absolute value of a
You are also doing the absolute value of b
Right, so you have to have at least two hardware bodies?
When two absolute value hardwares are used to do a
You are doing b at the same time
Because these two are at the same time
Then if you are divided into two states
For example, if you are in the first state, calculate t1 first.
The second state is calculated as t2
Then at this time you only need an absolute value hardware
You can use the same absolute value hardware
to find the absolute value of a
Then do the absolute value of b in the next state
so
Do you want to put them in the same state?
It depends on your plan
What you planned is different
The status of your entire circuit design is
Everything will be different
I'll go here first
emphasize this
So what is right?
There is no standard answer for you
You have to evaluate it yourself
You have to evaluate it yourself. That's right.
Because you can really divide it into one state
It can be viewed in two states
Do you want low cost or fast speed?
That's it
Then what do you do after you calculate t1 and t2?
You ask for x and y
So you see
The maximum value of t1 and t2 is x
Because t1 and t2 are actually already a
Is b definitely worth it?
Is it correct that the absolute value of a is the same as the absolute value of b?
Therefore, the smaller values ​​in t1 and t2
Put it in y
No problem here
You can find x and y here
Then the next state
You shift x right by 3 bits.
Shift y right one position and put it in t
y is shifted right by one position and placed at t4
what does that mean
What does T4 equal to 0.5 y?
Because you shifted y one position to the right
Then you shift x right three places and put it in T3
what does that mean
T3 is 0.125x because shifting one position to the right becomes 0.5
Shift right two places to 0.25
Shift three places to the right and it becomes 0.125
So T3 here is actually 0.125x
Then T4 is actually 0.5Y
So you have calculated this 0.5Y
So what are you going to do next?
Why do you want to subtract T3 from x?
Because T3 is 0.125X
Subtract 0.125X from x to get 0.875X
So this action is calculated as 0.875X
What's next?
You have to add these two
So your T4 is actually 0.5Y
Is that right? Your T5 T5 is 0.875x
0.5Y plus 0.875x
The result is placed in T6
Then this T6 will get the previous one.
The sum of these two
That t6
Then find the maximum value of x.
Put it on t7
Then it's done
Then let me talk about it again here
Re -emphasis primary
You
These two actions must be performed in the same state
Still divided into two states
This is your plan
So you can also
For example, I can also combine T4 and T5
Put it in the same state
I don’t want to be divided into two states
My name is T4
Then I will do subtraction with T4 at the same time.
Also do addition at the same time
Oh, that's okay too
No one said no
But your costs will be higher
so
You have to divide it into eight states from S0 to S7.
Still have to divide into 9 pieces, still have to divide into 5 pieces
You can plan this
But your plan is different
Your circuit is different
Just telling you this
So this
Which of your actions should be in the same state?
You can divide this
Then suppose that
So our premise is
Suppose you use the left side like this
This 8-state method assumes
I think this method is the simplest
Then we will use this method
no problem
In the case of this method
How do I register sharing
Because we are now going to do storage sharing
Storage sharing
In fact, here we
What we are talking about is mainly the sharing of temporary registers.
because of storage space
that storage space
In fact, what we discuss most here is the temporary register.
So storage sharing
In fact, it is the sharing of register
So how do we do register sharing?
That's it
Suppose I already know that I am divided into these 8 states
The 8 states from S0 to S7
Then we need to register for sharing. What do I want to do?
I first need to decide how many states there are
I just told you this
This depends on you
You can divide it from S0 to S7 or S0 to S9
You can also divide it into S0 to S4
You have to complete step 4, step 5, and step 6.
You can complete all 12 steps.
Then the circuit may be different.
So the first thing you have to decide is
How many states do you want to divide into?
After that, there is a state
You have to decide the lifetime of each variable
Because we just talked about
You can share
only in our lifetime
no overlap
in other words
I won't use it when you use it.
You won't use it when I use it
This way the two of us can share
We can share this storage space
The premise is that you won’t use it when I use it.
When you use it, I won’t use it.
Then the two of us can share it
So our life spans cannot overlap
So I have to determine the lifetime of each variable
Then the lifetime of each variable is determined.
I will know
I need at least a few temporary registers
Then I can design this circuit
Then let's take a look
Let's string this together
So you can see
From this state diagram on the left
I will draw the life cycle on the right
The lifetime of each variable
Schematic diagram
How to draw this schematic diagram?
It's actually very simple
You pay attention
In my S0 state, I read in a and b.
I read in the first variable
The first input is read in and placed into a
The second input is read in and placed in b
Right? Then let me ask you how long a will live.
Which variable's lifetime are we now asking for?
A and B are variables
How long will he live?
The life span means
How long will I live?
You pay attention
After A and B are calculated
A and B are used here, right?
Will anyone use my a and b later?
No
So I only need to live in one state a and b
So you see him like this
As long as a b is alive in the state of s1
Because you s
you were figured out
I'm alive here
You can calculate the absolute value
After the calculation, I can throw away AB.
Because he doesn't have to live anymore
So this is called his life span
What about after calculating t1 and t2?
Because after t1 and t2 are calculated,
There's no use for it here.
Therefore, the life cycle of t1 and t2 is also a state.
You should pay attention to the special one
For example, XY has been calculated, right?
Is it correct that x is used here?
You figure out x here
Here you need to use x to shift three places to the right
you are here
Also use x
You also need to use x here
So x wants me 1234 4 states
because you see
I calculated x here and will use it here
It will also be used here
To live, x must always be remembered
This should be remembered because x will be used later.
So I have to remember 4 states for this reason
Because someone behind me will use x
right?
So I want to live after x is calculated
Stay alive until you are used up here
Because the result of the operation on the right is placed on the left
So if this variable will be used
Then you have to live forever
What about y
y is not necessary. Look at y after calculating it.
Only this person will use y
Is there any y that needs to be used on the right side of the equal sign?
No, so y only needs one state
What about T3?
After t3 is calculated
Just live here
That's no problem
He is also in a state
But what about T4?
T4 counts here
T4 will be used here only after the calculation is done.
So after T4 is calculated, here must be alive.
There are two states to live in
So this is called his life span, that’s what it means
because you want
After I figured it out I used
A storage space to temporarily store it
right?
Then this storage space will be occupied all the time.
Because it is assumed that this value will be used later
This is called its life span
If this storage space
I release it for others to use today
The value I just calculated is gone.
So his premise is that
a b is calculated as long as it maintains a state T1
But x must be alive after it is calculated
You will be used up only if you stay alive until here.
So x has to change 4 states
So you can know
This is how we write it:
This is the status
Here are the variables
That horizontal axis is state
The vertical axis is the variable
You can make a cross out of it this way
It’s that variable that needs to stay alive.
Then make a mark
So we can figure out how
How many variables must be alive in each state?
The first state must have two variables
The second state must have two variables
The third state must have two variables
The fourth state must have 3 variables
The fifth state must have 3 variables
The sixth state must have two variables
The seventh state must have a variable
Then let me ask Dajia
How much storage space do you need at least?
This time will come, right here
Right? What does this mean?
There are two variables to remember in state one
There are two variables in state 2
In state 3, there are two temporary registers
Two scratchpads are needed
When in state 4
Because there are three that only need to be remembered
So in state 4
There must be at least three scratchpads
what does that mean
I ran through every state of the entire circuit
I need at least three registers
I want to take the most
To be alive in a certain state at the same time
The most variable
That is in
Both state 4 and state 5 require 3 temporary registers each.
So I need at least 3 scratchpads
Only then can
You can save all my information
That’s understandable here
This is called his life span
This variable has to live for so long
There is also this variable
Just live in one state
Then some variables need to live in two states
Then I'll know after we figure it out
I need at least 3 scratchpads
Then I need at least 3 temporary registers
I can
I just assume that my register number is called R1
R2,R3
I have three temporary registers
They are R1, R2, R3 respectively
Then I ask Dajia how do you save it?
It's actually very simple
He is like this here
You have to stay alive in this state a and b
So you see
I am in this state of s1
I also need at least two scratchpads
Then I will give my number
The value of a is placed in r1
The value of b is placed in r2
Right? Then what?
Reached next state
In the next state, I need to remember t1 and t2
That’s because you no longer need a and b.
So the storage space of a and b can be freed up
Then I put t1 on r1
T2 is put on R2 again
Well, as soon as you put t1 in, a will be covered.
That's because a won't be used later
It doesn't matter, we share the register
So I have the same scratchpad
Sometimes what is saved is a
Sometimes the deposit is t1
Sometimes I save x
Sometimes I save T7
I just use this concept
So you can see that my r1 and r2 are placed at a and b
Then what's next
r1, r2 are placed with t1, t2
Because you were later freed up
I’ll do another one next x
Then I put x in r1
Right because
R1 is used up here, and r2 is empty again
So I put x in r1, what about y?
y I assume I put it in r2
Oh, and then when we get here
Come in with your t4
You cannot place t4 on r1 at this time.
Because x wants to live forever
Then x is placed in r1
Just put your t4 in r2
Then you t3
Can be placed in another temporary register
r3 Then x will still be alive next
Then t4 is still alive
Then put your new t5 t5 into r3
That's it
Because you only have 3 scratchpads now
Then this is called temporary register sharing.
Then we have to see the results
You will know after seeing the results
Before looking at the results, let’s take a look at it again
If you don't share at all
Think about it
What you have to do is this
So what does it mean?
I need a temporary register to store it
b requires a scratchpad
T1 also needs one and t2 also needs one
x also wants one
I also need one for y. I also need one for T3. I also need one for T4.
All variables to the left of the equal sign
A temporary register must be used to store
So you can imagine me a
b t1 T2 x y
T3 T4 T5 T6 T7
Each of these uses a scratchpad
So I need a dozen temporary registers here
I want a dozen temporary registers
Only in this way can we save these dozen variables.
Then we just
We will know after sharing
Each state only requires up to 3 scratchpads
Because there is no overlapping relationship between life spans
So I just need 3 scratchpads
It can be covered
So my circuit will be designed like this
You see he only has 3 temporary registers
3 scratchpads
Then what did he put?
R1 we want to put a t1 x t7
R2 puts these 5
R3 contains these two
If you use this
Look
You put 4 variables here
Put 5 variables here
Put two variables here
So you now use 3 temporary registers to share
Watch it again
If you don't handle it specially
Each variable requires a temporary register
So you need a dozen scratchpads
What I am doing now is register sharing
After register sharing
I only need three scratchpads
But my circuit will be a lot more complicated.
You pay attention
What do you mean my circuit is very complicated?
Take a look
What is the first action
The first action is that I want to make a
Put the first input into a
Put the second input into b
So you can see my r1
This register
The first input of a should be connected to r1 here
because
After the first input comes in
This is what is called a
What about R2?
What to put in r2
Is it right to put the second input in r2?
So there will be a line here to put r2
Next
The absolute result of a must be connected to t1
So you can see you a
Was it placed in r1 just now?
Right, so you want a
You need to have an absolute value hardware when you come here.
Can help you calculate the absolute value
Then help him t1 after the absolute value of a
t1 is r1 again
So you would have a line
Take it back r1
Is that right? Take it back r1?
What about your second one?
You want b
The absolute value of b is placed in t2
Then you put b in r2
So the absolute value of your b
There is another issue of absolute value here
When you're done, you have to pull another thread back.
Why? Because your t2 is placed on r2
So there will be another one in your r2
that
So every line of this
There is a meaning behind it
For example, if you want to generate r1
a t1 X T7 is placed on r1
So you see that what will be placed in r1 is a
Then the absolute value of a
The absolute value of a is the so-called t1
That x
So these options can be selected into r1
It is to satisfy these four things
To be placed in r1
So every line has meaning behind it
You have 12345 five variables here that will be placed in r2
So you can see
Look, I have a selection line here
There are 5 inputs
These 5 inputs will be placed in r2
What about R3?
There are only two r3
So you see there will be two lines here on r3
Then it will be placed in r3
So you have to draw each line specially
In order to do this thing
You want to design
The result of which operation
To connect to r1 or r2
Or connect to r3
There is a meaning behind every line
It’s no longer random calls.
So now the question comes
we tell you
Why
We told you that you are not very good at register sharing.
You actually do academically
Why do you do it academically?
If you don't have special treatment
You need a dozen temporary registers, right?
If you want a dozen temporary registers
Do you want to make this circuit?
After I sorted it out like this, I found
At least 3 are enough
Because our state is
Three variables need to be saved
So I used three pausers
Then I will lay out the three temporary registers first.
Then each of these connections
I'll take a look at how my circuit looks like
My wiring will connect it one by one.
I ask you
Why is it academically meaningful?
When it comes to academics, take the time to do it
Then you earned seven or eight temporary registers
Because you only used 3
Less than ten times more than before
So you can earn 8 scratchpads
9 scratchpads
But what did you spend?
What you spent was labor
Because every line of your
You have to make a special trip to pick it up
this is the first thing
So you have to manually connect it yourself
What about the second one?
All your verilog code must be written down to the gate level.
See if you want to select a selector here
I need a website generator here
Then you have to pick up these modules one by one.
You can't do it at a very high level
Very behavioral to write
no way
So what you have to do is share
Once you decide to do something today, you have to do it manually
Then you need to down your circuit to gate level
That's why I say it is academically meaningful
But you don’t want this in the company
Because you want to earn these temporary registers
Your entire design time will be very long
And it may take a long time for you to debug.
So he
It may not be necessary. It may not be necessary.
But you can know how he did it
Register sharing is like this
When can it be shared?
I won't use it when you use it.
wait until
After I deposited your value, mine was overwritten.
So I might save it first.
Then my life is over
Anyone who wants to use my storage space
I don't care.
Because I won't be used again
This is what he meant
My AB is used here
AB is not used later.
I can give up my AB space.
Then I saved x here
But because someone will use x later
So I x will live longer
Then this one is used
So Register sharing is like this
But I have just stressed again and again
He may not use it
Because the cost to you is very high if he continues to use it.
What I mean by cost is yours
Design costs will become higher
Although your hardware costs are reduced
But your design costs are getting higher.
After talking about the first resource sharing
The second thing we want to look at is called functional
unit sharing
that is
Compute this and this is the storage unit
The storage unit here is the temporary register.
Sharing of temporary registers
The second share is functional unit
The functional unit is these additions, subtractions, multiplications and divisions
These absolute values
The commonality of these operations
So what is functional unit sharing?
Let’s take the example just now and you can see
I'm going to add
Suppose I want to add
I'm going to do subtraction below
Add above
Next, add
Then of course I can use the same adder
do this twice
But if I want to add
You need to reduce the following
Then if you don’t have a special design
Then you need to use an adder
use a subtractor
The function of the so-called functional unit is like this
I can
Can I design a hardware
Both addition and subtraction can be done
This is called an adder and subtractor
Then I'll choose
Let me choose
What I want to do this time is add
What we need to do next time is reduce
So if you could design one like this
This is called functional unit sharing
So he is like this
You do the same calculation
we can do sharing
For example, this plus this plus this
I can do it twice with the same adder
Because he was fucked at different times
This is called functional unit sharing
This is a sharing of the same operation
I today
This plus uses the same hardware as this plus
Because if you don’t have a special design
In Verilog
We can use two different hardware
Do it in parallel
Then I can use a hardware now
Add this first
Then add this
Because he was at different times
Then I can also design an adder and subtractor
Both addition and subtraction can be done
So this functional unit sharing
Contains me sharing the same operation
What is the second thing I share?
different operations
but similar
Then this
functional unit sharing and Register sharing just now
Same
Let’s take a look at what the concept of sharing is
This thing of mine exists here today
Then I save things that remember me.
When can I save you?
My life ends today
The value I calculated will no longer be used by others.
I can give you my space
you can come here
The same goes for the sharing of this operation.
I am today
If this addition and this addition are at different times,
Then I can use an additive hardware
Then let him do it twice
But
When not to use the same piece of hardware twice?
If you add it, I will add it too
Then he also wants to add
Then we need three hardware bodies
Because when you add, I will add too
Then he also wants to add
Let's make it impossible
Then I will need 3 hardware bodies at this time
So which one should be shared?
The lifetime of that addition is different.
I won’t add it when you add it.
Then I won’t add him when he does.
We all have different times
You can do it three times with one addition
But if you add
Your added life span
The life span of this addition overlaps with mine.
That won't work either.
Because you said so, I will add it too
That requires two different hardware
Then if there is another person
The same is true for life span
Then I need three different hardware bodies
so
As long as it talks about Sharing
You have to pay attention to this
It's a matter of life span
Is there any overlap? Is there any overlap?
So this is called functional unit sharing
Then this functional unit sharing
What does it mean?
For example, I can use a hardware
It can do the minimum
Then I can also use one piece of hardware to do the maximum value.
Then I have a hardware
Can be a maximum or minimum value
Then you pay attention
Whether you are the minimum or maximum
This hardware is used
a subtractor
Then add some circuits
can become a minimum value
In other words, this circuit should be able to do subtraction
That can also be the minimum value
Because he is a
substractor
He is a subtraction
Then you can also deform it a little bit
He can do the maximum
You can also transform it again
It can be either a maximum or a minimum value.
It depends on how you choose
Then this is called hardware sharing.
functional unit sharing
In the same way, you move left
You move right one position and right three positions
You can also put it together
but
Because the cost of the shifter is actually relatively low
This comparison doesn't make much sense
So let’s look down
You see, he has designed a hardware here now
What can this hardware do?
absolute value
It can also be a minimum value or a maximum value.
In other words, this hardware
Because he used an adding machine
with two selectors
There is also an XOR
This hardware can do both absolute value
Then you can also do the minimum value or the maximum value
What about this hardware?
This hardware can be added
You can also do absolute values ​​or subtractions.
He basically uses an adding machine
Plus some other logic gates
He can do these three functions at the same time
So this is called
functional unit sharing
My hardware
Can do different things at the same time
Just different
but
Similar operations
So this is our understanding here.
Then let's take a break
Then continue from here
Just rest for 10 minutes