Then let's go next
Next
Continue here
This is back to the one just now
The r1, r2, r3 I just talked about
3 scratchpads
After we just talked about register sharing
Only 3 scratchpads are used
Then you pay attention
I still have a lot of computing units here
So the functional unit sharing we just talked about
that is
Someone asked you to say
Those computing units are shared by them
you have a way to
Are the computing units below shared?
that is
I can do it together
You have to think like this
I'm going to make this today
No, this is the absolute value
Minimum value I assume that I want to make a hardware
You can do both absolute value and minimum value at the same time.
His cost will definitely not be the same as this one
For example, suppose the cost is one
This cost is another
Originally, you wanted to make two, so two pairs were required, right?
Then we have to do it together
Maybe 1.3
The cost of 1.3 So this so-called
The concept of functional unit sharing is also the same.
Can you make this, this, and this together?
Originally it was 1,1,1
Then if you do it together now, it may be 1.6
Then 1.6 is smaller than 3
This is called functional unit sharing
Can I save a little less in the temporary register just now?
Because my life span is different
So what are you doing today?
You can see
This just came out
It's quite complicated for you guys.
Can these functional units be shared?
but still the same
When can functional unit be shared?
Same as scratchpad
Unless you do this calculation
I do this operation at different times
I won't do it when you do it.
You won't do it when I do it.
Then I can do these two
Sharing can be designed to do two things at the same time
Of course, it's the same if you want to share it with this one.
I can't do it when you do it
You can't do it while I'm doing it
This way my hardware can be shared, okay so
functional unit sharing here
He will go down
Can I do it?
Use a subtractor and then
Make the minimum
I use a subtractor to do the maximum
can i make one
Can be used as minimum or maximum
Then I can even make one
The hardware performs absolute minimum, maximum and absolute values ​​at the same time.
good
Then I use a piece of hardware to do addition, absolute value, and subtraction at the same time.
of course
But the premise
You want to put these operations on the same hardware
cannot be done at the same time
So how to design this circuit?
In fact, it’s the same as just now
Register sharing is very similar to
So let's take a look
Let's pull out this formula first.
This is the state we distribute
From S0 to S7
Okay, let me say it again
You can also divide it into 9 states. You can also divide it into 20 states.
Your status is different
Your entire design will be different.
Okay, then we are now divided into 8 states.
This is how you divide
So you can see what you did in s1
s1 made two absolute values
So your absolute value of two is marked like this
What about s2? s2 is the maximum and minimum value
So one maximum value and one minimum value, right?
And what about S3
In this state of S3, you have done two shifts
S4 you made a subtraction
S5 you made a plus
If so, just mark it
So what did you do with S6?
You should mark it well
Okay, it’s the same thing. It’s the same thing if you want to share it.
What are the only situations where you can share?
Those actions cannot be performed in the same state
So what should we do?
In fact, he has a look like this
like information engineering department
The kind of graph theory method that I am more familiar with
In fact, what is the graph theory method?
I am like this
Do I have two absolutes to do now?
Then I drew a dotted line
Why draw a dotted line?
The representative said they were in the same state
Then I have minimum and maximum to do.
Because he is in the same state
so
I also drew a dotted line for minimum and maximum
Okay then what
I have another shift
Since there is no cost, it doesn't matter much.
I have a subtraction and an addition
That subtraction and addition are in different states
So he has no dotted line
I have additions and subtractions
Okay, let me ask everyone
Look at the operations required for each state.
Each state requires operations
Operations required for each state
If you use this table to figure it out
I ask everyone that every status
At least a few operations are required
There are only two operations at most.
Each state has at most two operations
Right? So you can imagine
In fact, I only need two computing units
Just two operations can complete
Because in every state of my life
There will only be at most two operations to be done
This is how he sees it
Because you have so many calculations to do
But in different states there will be
different operations to be done
but
If you look at it this way
every state of your
There are only two operations to be done at the same time
So I can actually do it with just two pieces of hardware.
You watch it again and come back here
what does this mean
From your side
Here 12345678 did you use 8 hardware?
Then we will tell you now
Each state only has at most two pieces of hardware to do.
So actually I only have two hardware bodies here
I can handle it.
I only have two pieces of hardware and I can do it.
So I can do it with two pieces of hardware.
This is the conclusion reached here
I need at least two
Two operations and two hardware
Then I came to the dotted line today
Okay, so what's next?
What he actually uses is good stuff like graph theory.
Do I only need two pieces of hardware?
Okay, then I'll circle it. I'll circle it like this.
Can I be like this?
These two are circled together
These four are circled together. This is a kind of circle.
Look
Then it’s okay to circle like this
Well, then, then, you pay attention, pay attention, pay attention
No matter you circle it like this or this way
Let me ask you, how many red circles have you circled?
Two groups?
Because you only need two hardware bodies
Right? Then why are you
Those with dotted lines cannot be enclosed in the same hardware body.
There is a dotted line because it means he has to do it at the same time
Then he needs to be assigned different hardware
The dotted line means he has to do it at the same time
He needs to be assigned different hardware
So I can circle
This is a circle method. These two groups are
These four groups
You can also do this in groups of 3
Of course, these three can be exchanged.
no problem
Then the result will be different
So you can see
you can
You do the math like this
you will know
In fact, you only need two sets of hardware
So in other words
What this means is that I have a hardware that can also
My hardware can do absolute values
You can also do the minimum value
I have another hardware
Can do absolute value
Can be the minimum value
Can do subtraction. Can do addition. Good.
Then if you use it like this, say I have it
A piece of hardware that can do absolute minima and addition
My other hardware
You can do absolute maximum value and subtraction
Okay, then, do we want this or this?
Then we can do the math
What if
I have a hardware with absolute value and minimum
Then I probably need a few logic gates
Several adders, several logic gates
Then if these four are in a group
Then I probably need this
Okay, then my total sum is two, one, one, two, two
Okay, what if I divide it like this?
Am I in a group?
Absolute value, minimum value, plus a group of these three
Then I want 1,1,1,2
Then these three groups
Absolute value, maximum value, minus one, one, one, two
That adds up to two, one, one, two, two
you will find
In fact, you use the above division method
Or the following division
Your total cost is the same
So the representative said that actually both divisions are acceptable.
But you must divide into two groups
Okay, so what about your circuit after you divide it?
The circuit will be much cleaner like this
Have you ever looked at what it was like?
It turned out to be like
It turns out it’s like this, right?
Look at the three temporary registers
But there are so many functional units at the back
Now after you divide it into two groups
After being divided into two groups, it looks like this
You still have three temporary registers, right?
You have two sets of hardware and this is one way
absolute value,minimum
Absolute value, maximum, addition, subtraction
It’s the above division method
Then if you look at your line, it will become
A bit simpler
Then why can these two be grouped together?
It’s because it’s absolutely worth doing it
I will never do the minimum
When doing minimum, you will not do absolute value.
So you can group it together
Then these four can be grouped together
It’s because you can’t do it when doing absolute values.
maximum, and I can’t do any additions.
I won’t do any reduction either.
because you see
When you do absolute value
In fact, nothing else was done.
So this is how you divide it
These operations can be grouped into the same group
It's because their time is different
If the time is the same, you have already used a dotted line.
So you just put it
When they gather together, they are divided into different categories
Then there's no problem
So this is a way?
One of unit sharing
This is probably what you would do manually today.
Then if you look at your line, it will become
A bit simpler
good
If you are in another way today
That is to say, these three
Then his circuit will be different
You see this is
Two or four
Then this one is three by three
Then his lines will look different.
But the cost is the same
Because we just calculated it here
Basically his cost is the same
So it should be said that both methods are possible
It will be all right
Because the cost is the same
You just need to divide into two groups.
Then why is this shifter not regulated here?
Because the shifter is basically free of cost
So we don’t consider the shifter here.
Just consider these more complicated ones
Okay, of course
say it again
You have to think like this
The absolute referring cost is assumed to be one
minimum is one
Then you were originally 1+1
It originally cost 2, but now you put it together and it might cost 1.5
But 1.5 is still smaller than 2
Then you originally wanted one, two, three, four or four.
You're probably sitting together at 1.8 right now
But 1.8 is still much smaller than 4, which is good
You have to think about it this way
That makes sense
This is called functional unit sharing
As long as we do this operation
are to be done at different times
I can share this functional unit
Okay then
Here we have to mention a little bit
We talked about two sharing
We talked about two shared
that is
storage sharing and functional unit sharing
A classmate just came and asked a very good question.
He said: Teacher, when we are taking the exam
our homework
We need to optimize the area
I want to reduce costs
Do I want to use this?
Basically you won't use it
Why
We just listened
You won't get down to this level anymore
In fact, our homework or exam
You just need to put your Verilog
Just write behavior tVerilog
We didn't get this
because you want
How scary it is to take exams like this
You see, your circuit is very small.
Your circuit is very small
So you can calculate 3 temporary registers
Then you can also manually enter this line
You have to think that if your temporary register is 20
20 pieces should not be picked up manually.
Because you have to finish drawing this page before you can write about him.
Verilog
Because every connection you make has meaning
so
After you drew this picture manually,
Shine again
Print this Verilog
That’s why I said you are writing at gate level.
So you need to optimize this storage
Basically the questions on our exam
No such requirement
Homework is not too scary because of this.
Because our topic is relatively big
We are just giving this example
As a small question, you can do this
If you really have to do it manually for a big problem
That's unlikely
Almost almost impossible
But I say it makes sense academically
Because when you were doing your thesis
Because your thesis might be about writing an adder
You may be making a simple circuit
Then there are 3 less temporary registers at this time
5 less registers
Or functional unit sharing
This all contributes
These are all academic contributions
But you're writing Verilog
Go down to this level and write
Let me tell you, you can’t finish this homework
You can’t finish your homework and you can’t finish your exams either.
So we didn't ask for this
You just need to put verilog us
I remind you in class that you should write well, just write it well
What if
That's a matter of the level of your algorithm.
I definitely didn’t ask you to go down to this level.
Absolutely not
那functional unit sharing
I can't guarantee it
There must be no storage sharing
functional unit sharing
If your topic is big
Because you want me to be functional
Our current function is very small
What is our function?
Adjustment
It's just an absolute value operation, right?
Okay, then you need to enlarge it.
This is the only function you have
When will you do functional unit sharing?
You have to imagine
If I say today
For example, let's say I am a compressed circuit
This function is compressed into this area
Then your other actions today are very big
Then press this area into a small area
If this can be shared
Then this may cost a lot.
If you don’t share
For example, when student A is in the crimping area
Classmate B is pressing
Student B is pressing at the same time
You will need 3 copies of this
So I can’t even guarantee you functional unit sharing.
But every time you make a share
You know that. You don’t want to share it so much.
That should be said
If there were only these additions, subtractions, multiplications and divisions
You don't have to share a functional unit.
You don't have to, you don't have to, absolutely you don't have to
Absolutely not
If a small circuit like ours
You don't need
Then what I'm talking about is that if you want it, you need to enlarge it.
Your functional unit sharing
If you are making a very complicated circuit
Think of it as a big circuit
You will need three for this circuit
Three such large circuits
Then your costs may become very high
But if your time is up
B will not do it when a does it
Then you yourself
In fact, we need to use the same hardware to plan
But if addition, subtraction, multiplication and division are like this
It doesn't matter
The impact is not that big
Okay, this won't let you
If you really want to go down to that
It's troublesome
So, and you can see
Actually you did this
It is possible that it will go down to the gate level.
But if your module is fixed
Your module is very large. In fact, there may be one more state.
Just redraw your state diagram.
So it should be said like this
So although we gave this example
Don't think about it
When we take the exam
What register sharing
Come and put it to good use
Then you won’t be able to finish writing like this
I can only tell you this
Then this is meaningless
well
Then wait a minute
The third lesson
The teaching assistant will send that
The fourth assignment
We're going to give out the fourth assignment
At the same time, he will review
The one who took the midterm exam will give you an example
That is, he will take the midterm exam
How to write it? I sorted it out in detail.
Then I'm still the same here
I want to tell you something
You must do well if you don't do well in the midterm exam
If you do well in the exam, there's no problem
Because I have confessed
I've already discussed that with the teaching assistant.
In addition to following our final exam
The midterm exam is somewhat similar
So you must fully understand the midterm exam
If you go back and rewrite yourself
Can write very well
Of course the teaching assistant will talk today
I will take the midterm exam
Then I think the best way is
He has a code for you to see
You can give it a rough look and then go back and rewrite it yourself.
Then do it again then
You will know that your code is different from others
Where
Then you must do well in your midterm exam.
Then you do this for your final exam
If you don't do well on the midterm exam
It will be easier for you to make up for your final exam.
because we will
Try to be an extension of the midterm exam
I have discussed it with the teaching assistant
The simplest way
I hope everyone can pass
Because really
I don’t want to be you either
That
Then this and this
Let's stop here for a moment
Let's take a look at this
To encourage everyone
Everyone worked very hard to write the program.
We want to encourage everyone
Look at last year
I think everyone should have seen that
some news
How much did MediaTek spend last year?
Then how much did Novatek spend last year?
So why is this happening?
In fact, you can tell at a glance
MediaTek’s revenue the year before last was 320 billion
Last year it surged to 490 billion
So last year’s turnover was that of the year before
170 billion more
There is also the one from the past
There is also that next one
I will give a lecture at the Department of Engineering next week
It should be next week
I invited them to give a speech at the Department of Engineering
Novatek's turnover is only 80 billion
Last year, 135 billion
Just imagine him, he changes from 80 billion to 135 billion
Moreover, look at this IC factory
The profit is 30%
It’s just that he is not 3% or 5%
his his that
The profit is 30%
And if you look at United Wing, he said 1,350
130 billion 130 billion Novatek has less than 3,000 people
Then look at the output value of each person
Less than 3,000 employees
Almost all of them are engineers
Less than 3,000 employees, he can’t reach 1,300
What about Realtek? It was originally the same one.
He should have been close to 77 billion originally.
It also reached 100 billion last year
That Qijing Optoelectronics turned out to be
More than 20 billion. Last year, it reached more than 40 billion.
Qijing Optoelectronics is the one that built the third motor hall now.
You can see that this is
That's also because you can see
The year before last
So Taiwan
IC design enters top ten in the world in 2020
In fact, only the first three are in the top ten.
Last year even the wonders came in
So last year, there were actually 4 companies in the top ten.
Of course, this is actually more than just that.
For example, Phison
Look at Phison, it only made over 10 billion last year
No, because if he connects the module
His turnover last year was about 60 billion
Because he doesn't just sell chips
Weilong is written here
He's not just selling chips when it comes to group acting.
He also sells modules
so
But you see, his module didn’t include it.
Otherwise, Phison actually didn’t even make modules last year.
It’s not just about making more than 10 billion
It’s 60 billion
So this is actually the whole
Why is the salary high and then that?
It's probably because of this or this.
So you can see
Last year it was all over, so this year maybe
I think it might not be as bad as last year
Not that good. Sorry.
It's not as good as last year
But you just have to be in the middle
That should be the entire turnover
That
What are you going to do if you
I didn't do well on the midterm exam.
Then you still have to work hard
I can only say this
Because actually I don’t know how to help you
But you are good
Write well. You write well and then
You can ask the teaching assistant and then you can put
Today because
Because I specially confessed today
The teaching assistant must explain that
That midterm exam
If you don't do well in the midterm exam,
a chance for my classmates
You should at least trace code
Then what should I tell you?
this matter
It just depends on whether you want to spend time
You can do it as long as you take the time
You can definitely do it if you take the time
Then I last time
I should have given you an example.
I
Before I went to Chengdu University to teach
I still teach at Nantai University
My first graduate student
That is, the graduate student who founded the mountain
It was collected at Nan Tai University.
I am the first graduate student in Southern Taiwan
He turned out to be an elevator worker
That
How do you calculate that your level should be better than his?
The so-called elevator worker means
He actually turned out to be a student from a fifth college
That
Did you know that the fifth college is where you go after graduating from junior high school?
That’s because he has been practicing in five specialties for five years
Those fifth majors were because he was "too good"
So I didn’t graduate from the fifth secondary school in five years.
Didn't he go to the army after graduation?
After serving in the army, he went to work as an elevator worker
Then the elevator worker
In fact, he only earns more than 10,000 yuan a month
that 24 hours then
And because the elevator only needs to be replaced once
He wants it. He wants it.
Were you called to repair the elevator?
Later, he wanted to think that it would be impossible to live like this for the rest of his life.
He
Come to Nantai University to study evening department
Is the night department because of the fifth major?
After graduating from fifth college
Then I will study in my junior and senior years.
Just get that
Bachelor's certificate
Because their fifth junior college is actually counted as three years of high school.
Then I will be a freshman or sophomore
You may not know this well
Then he only needs to practice for two more years
It’s like a junior or senior year
He can get a college diploma
But his
At that time in Nantai
The night department has not graduated yet
I passed the exam
The graduate school of the department where I teach
Because it was the first
The first batch of graduate students
It's a good test.
That is, you only need to teach for 1,500 or 2,500 that you signed up for.
I'll definitely get there
Because no one wants to take the exam
That
Because it's hard for him to imagine
Some I I I give you an example you know
Are private school graduate schools good or not?
Imagine that situation
Questions from our institute
There are no multiple-choice questions or fill-in questions.
Why do you ask fill-in questions and multiple-choice questions?
Because there is a standard answer, he will get 0 points
A student with a score of 0 cannot be admitted.
So because there are too few people taking the exam
I admitted 30 people today
Maybe only 20 people come to take the exam
In order to make money, the school must admit everyone
What should I do?
All require quizzes
Q&A: All he needs to do is sign and write "Teacher, you are so great"
I can give him 3 points
He won't be 0 points
A score of 0 cannot be admitted.
The Ministry of Education has strict regulations
So you know why you can't do multiple choice questions and
Filler question?
Because fill-in questions and multiple-choice questions have standard answers.
If he writes every question wrong
That's 0 points
If you score 0 points, you will not be admitted.
So you must ask questions
He just wrote two words
The teacher is very handsome
Give him another 10 points and he will be admitted.
Well, after he comes in
I said I wanted to talk about the first batch of graduate students
He doesn't know anything when he comes in
Never learned C code
Stop talking about Verilog
I asked him to read a paper
He looked it up from the first word to the last
I don't know how to see it either
Not from beginning to end
Then I want to say that this is not possible
Because he has to practice English well
He won't graduate in two years
Just practice English
because
you know that english
How strong is English? Let me give you an example.
Is S-E-T set correct?
If you see a set of
you will think
It should be about something in a group
But you know the word for this set
sucks
set may be a setting
It may be a collection
There are many possible meanings.
Then he has never read the original document.
do you know
He saw a set of
He just randomly picked one from 20 possibilities.
translate him
Then I will say
How can you understand this paper?
Impossible
Because he looked up every word
Then it goes around and around like this
Just like this
Because he has never read the original document
so
There is no such thing as that
Then I don't know what to do
I said there are only two things
You just need to do two things
In fact, he still has classmates who graduated in two years
I said you only need to do two things
The first one is to learn c code well
Just simple c
Then he won't
Okay, trace the program that teacher wrote before
If you don't know how, I'll teach you
Ok then Verilog looks like this
Just took my course
I started writing this after finishing it
That is to write well
What about after you finish writing?
He graduated in two years
Then when I went out to work, I was actually very pitiful.
Because his English is bad
In fact, until he went to work, he
He feels that he is very pitiful
So colleagues write e-mails in English
He didn't dare to go back. He said he was coming to find me.
So that's English is so bad
What will happen then?
In fact, in my laboratory, that is learning
I said your English is so bad
It is impossible to write an English e-mail
You just need to do one thing.
Understand the error message
Do you want to check your error message?
When you debug today, throw in the Verilog code.
He will give error message
Now you should read the error message often
Then you have to understand
At least he can understand the error message and debug it.
With one move, he entered the world of martial arts.
Then I will say that time
In fact, about twenty years ago
Then I told him to go
Hsinchu Science Park because we need to do IC design
Only go to Hsinchu Science Park
There are more job opportunities
He only went in once
When he entered VIA
Because he will come back
He often comes back to me and says: Teacher
beside
What national university is it from?
A lot of pressure
I said it doesn't matter, just do it well
Just do whatever people tell you to do
So he is in VIA
At that time, actually before VIA
Thirty years ago, VIA was now MediaTek.
You may not know
VIA used to make that computer chip
Now MediaTek
more than thirty years ago
But 20 years ago when my students went
This is already the case
His Vision
It’s already very bad. The annual salary is about 100.
Probably close to 100 or so
Then why does he even accept private schools?
It was over there before
Finally survived
But actually he has a principle
Then it's possible that he turned out to be an elevator worker
Have you worked hard
He will feel that
Be serious
He gets off work at 10 o'clock, otherwise he gets off work at 11 o'clock
I think so
More tolerant
That means you concentrate on it
Later he went to VIA
VIA has been doing this for five or six years
Then his boss happened to jump in
Other companies
Then there happened to be a shortage in the past few years.
Then asked him if he wanted to go
He went to the new company
That company was the second largest in Taiwan at that time.
At that time, MediaTek was the largest
The second largest is the morning glow
In fact, when he jumped, I guess
Because he is a student, we can't ask too detailed questions.
I guess
At that time, his signing bonus should have been 3 million.
But he really used to be an elevator worker
This is what he told me himself
24 hours on call
At that time, the signing bonus was 3 million
Then drive one
volvo RV
Come back to me
Okay, let's go to Chenxi.
Later, Mo Chenxi was acquired by MediaTek
Later he was at MediaTek
So actually this matter
Just want
I like to use this example to encourage everyone
Then as long as you are willing to take the time
Then go get this done
because of this
There is actually quite a shortage of people in this field.
The field of IC design
What he's afraid of is that you don't want to spend that time
As long as you are willing to take the time to learn it well
In fact, your future
Actually, to put it more plainly, this kind of thing
This kind of salary can't be worse than that of a doctor
because of you
Because there used to be many
Parents or students will want to study as a doctor
That doctor actually works very hard.
Have to be on duty at night or something?
Often have to stay awake
What what
What are you doing without sleeping for 36 hours straight?
And what about covid-19 now?
What SARS
It's easy to get hurt easily. It's easy to get shot.
Right? But I think engineers are
As long as you do it well, it will be relatively safe.
So I still have to encourage you
So wait a moment and let’s talk about it like this
During the midterm exam, do you really want to
Listen very carefully
Because if you don’t do well in the midterm exam
If you have any questions, please ask the teaching assistant.
Then when you go back, write it yourself
Good because we have adjusted the time
So you can imagine after we finish today
Today is April 20th
We will have final exams at the end of May
Okay so you have a month left
Can strengthen your Verilog
If you Verilog
I didn’t write my previous homework seriously
You have one month left to strengthen
Then you should work hard this month
Then you
We have finished the final exam and have final homework
That still encourages everyone
as long as you take the time
You should gain something in the end
What I'm afraid of is that you don't take the time
Then let's go down, so
resource optimization
resource optimization you except these two
In addition to storage space and functional sharing
Another thing you can do is bus sharing.
What is bus sharing?
That is
Bus Sharing
Then why do we need to share the bus?
because you can see
Look there's a lot of wiring here
We have just arrived at this
Are the three temporary registers correct?
We just need 3 temporary registers and then what?
Are the two arithmetic units right? OK
We've streamlined it to this
Or it can be both
Three scratchpads and then two arithmetic units
We've streamlined it down to this, okay
So what else can be streamlined now?
These wiring problems
These lines are actually quite messy.
Then if each register is 32bit
did you know
This is connected to 32bit, 32bit
This is because this is just drawing a line
But
If it is 32bit, he will have 32 at the same time
Then this one too
so what
Is there any way we can use a concept like a bus
Because our next step is bus sharing
It's like a bus, shared by everyone
bus concept
What about line sharing?
a bit like saying
It will be cleaner if you tidy up that line.
This is the concept of the whole line
I hope I can tidy up my line
Then he will be cleaner
Then this is called bus sharing
Then you want to reorganize the line?
Still the same came
This is the purpose of bus
For example, busbar. We know busbar
that is
You need to transfer the data from here to here
Then I can connect this bus
Everyone shares this cable
Then you can pick it up too
Then he can pick it up too
Everyone can connect to this bus
It's good without a problem
But here comes the problem
If student a is saving information,
I will upload it again
Then classmate C uploaded the message. No.
because of a bus
add a line
Someone above passed it on
When that person passes it, no one else can pass it.
Right? So the concept of busbar
It is shared by everyone
Just like the concept of bus bus means
For example, I drove from Tainan High Speed ​​Rail Station to
Tainan City National Cheng Kung University
Then the concept of my bus is to share the fare with everyone.
right?
It costs me NT$3,000 to drive from Tainan High Speed ​​Rail to National Cheng Kung University
Everyone who comes up shares it.
Pay this money together
Then everyone will pay less
The concept of bus sharing is this
If everyone shares this bus
Now the cost is lower
But it is shared
But there is a problem with sharing
When classmate a threw the information up,
Classmate b cannot throw it away. Classmate c cannot throw it away.
Because only one person can drop one line at a time
That is, there can only be one per line
In other words, look
That means this
If we all share a line
This person loses 101
Then I can't lose it
Because otherwise if he loses 101, then I lose 010
Then on this line you lose 0 and I lose 1
So is this line 0 or 1?
I have no idea
So the bus concept means
I don’t use it when you use it.
You don’t have to be nice when I use it
Then you see
Ours
I can straighten out the title
Using the bus concept I can wire it into
like this
Look, it will be very clean here.
It's not like this just now. It was a mess here just now.
Now I'll line it up like this, okay
But when it's like this
What should we pay attention to
For example bus1
R1 is connected to bus1
What does it mean when r3 is connected to bus1?
r3 cannot be used when r1 is using bus1
When using r3
r1 cannot be used
Because only one person can use it
Because the concept of this bus is like this
I don’t use it when you use it.
I don’t use it when others use it.
Well that's it
Then you have bus1, bus2, bus2 connected to r2
Then down below, you still have bus3, and the same goes for bus4.
You see there are two people in bus3
you can throw
I can also throw it away
Then I won’t throw it away when you throw it away.
When I throw it, you don’t throw it away.
Well, this is the concept of bus
So the bus is basically a bit like this
Actually, this is a bus connection
He just uses one
tri-state gate
What can a tri-state gate do? You see, it is actually
Your value is connected to mine.
Everyone has received this line
But I have a control
I used a tri-state gate here
I can control when I say you are okay and I am not okay
When I can get through, you can’t.
That's because he is
If enable comes, it will pass
enable did not come, I regarded it as high impedance
That high impedance is a bit like an open circuit
That is to say, I enable
He always knows when he comes
You can throw the data into this bus
If enable is not turned on, it will become high impedance.
High impedance
It's like a broken circuit
It means our line is broken
What does this mean?
The two of us need to use this bus
Then I will control it here.
Either you or I can understand
So when you pass
Your value can come over
Then my side will be disconnected.
High impedance is a bit like an open circuit
So my value won’t come over
Just wait until I get through. It will be through me.
Then your side will have high impedance
like you are a disconnect
Then use this to ensure that
We only have one person
good
So if we take the topic we just asked
How do we do this?
Okay, let's take a look
You just did this
Okay, then I'm going to start reorganizing the line now.
I want to use the bus concept
Then what if I use the bus concept?
well
Then let's assume
We assume this is the case
Your r1 is A, t1, x, t7
r2 is B, t2, y, t3, t5, t6
R3 is equipped with T4
Just based on these variable assumptions
This is what we put
This is our premise
And then you now have these two pieces of hardware
Okay, now I'm going to start reorganizing the line.
well
I'm going to start reorganizing the line, okay?
Then let me ask everyone
Now I assume there is a bus
Can I
Take r1 and r2 and connect them to this bus.
No, no
No, because r1 stores a
r2 stores b
I'm in this state
I will read out a at the same time
At the same time, read out b
Because I want to calculate his absolute value
Right? So I'm in r1
When I'm in this state
I want to read a and b at the same time
One is placed in r1 and the other is placed in r2.
So you must use two different buses
This way I can read a and b at the same time
Okay, so you watch out.
The bus you come out of is r1 and use bus1.
R2 is better with bus2
Then our doubt now is
then why do you
r3 and r1 will use the same bus
it's because you see
Is your r3 equipped with T4?
When your T4 is blocked
You need to block the other one
When t4 is taken out for calculation
This way
There is t4 here
Then the other thing to do is T5
Where is T5 placed?
r2
So you see these two moving like this at the same time
Then you r3
when moving
When r3 moves, your r1 will not actually move.
When your t4 moves
All r1 can move
So you can use two buses smoothly
Then why can these two be merged?
Why aren't r1 and r2 on the same bus?
It's because they are at the same time
Then r1 and r3 can
It's because
When I was studying T4
r1 will not move
Then when my r1 is moving
r3 will not move
So his line will
I can put it together
That's the same reason
Check here too
Why this bus3
This one will receive this
It must be something
It’s just that these three people will never move at the same time.
There must be only one person moving
Only one of these three people moved
What about these three people?
Why are they connected together?
Because this person won't move when he moves.
This guy won't move when he moves.
Okay, but let's not move here at the same time.
It can be so good
So this bus sharing is actually the same concept.
For the three sharings, you can think about why
The concept is the same
you
When you use it, I can't use it, it must be like this
Because that’s what sharing is
Sharing
Why are temporary registers shared?
When you save, I won’t save.
When I save, you don’t save.
Right, so the life spans cannot overlap?
Assume that it was all my fault
Then wait until I don't need to go out
I'll give you the space
This is called storage sharing
The same goes for functional unit sharing
If you don't do these two operations at the same time,
I don't do it when you do it
You don't do it when I do it
Then you can do it together
Shared hardware
to achieve the goal of cost reduction
The same goes for bus sharing
I won’t pass it on when you pass it on
When I pass it on, you don’t pass it on
Then the two of us can share a bus.
Okay, if we both want to pass it on too
Then I will use two buses.
Just like this, okay
When r1 passes, r2 also has to go.
Then the two of us need to use different buses.
but
After the information of r1 is released, r3 will not be released.
When r3 comes out, r1 will not come out.
Then we can share a bus
I can make my lines leaner
And you can
The planning is better
but still the same
I'll tell you
Each of these is very troublesome to do.
123 Good
Even to the last Register
Same thing
The same is true for Register merging
It will make your circuit very complicated
So basically
our
Most probably won't use it
That is, at least these two will definitely not
Then I will tell you about this.
Large-scale functional unit sharing is possible
You just have to pay attention when you compete.
If there is a large functional unit
Or a relatively big topic
Maybe you should pay attention to it
Otherwise
In fact, because after using it
will make your circuit design become
Very very complicated
So in principle, today we will
After talking about the previous resource sharing 123 3
Sharing of constituent units
Sharing of the third computing unit
and bus sharing
Then the remaining unit
We’ll talk about this next week
Then in the next class I will
Give time to teaching assistants
He will come and give the fourth assignment
That's because I have to give him a whole class
Because he still has to review the midterm exam
So I left get out of class two minutes early
If you forget the questions for the midterm exam
Please review it quickly
Then wait until the assistant teacher comes to explain.
you will know better
Is his answer available in Moodle?
Then take a quick look at it, okay?
Then he will explain it later, OK.
Then let’s finish class 2 minutes early for this period.