Hello, classmates
Then the third quarter is up to me.
Let’s talk about the sample code for the midterm exam.
And our homework 4
That's because our final exam will use
There is still a midterm exam
Make some modifications to the content of Assignment 3
Then use it as our final exam question
So that is
Wait a minute, if you take the midterm exam
Because many students take mid-term exams
Question 2 is not written down
so
If your question 2 has not been written before
Students must listen carefully to understand that
How to answer question 2 of the midterm exam correctly
Okay, then I will start with the midterm exam.
So the next slide is what we have put on
The one on Moodle
Slide the slide and my answer will always be based on this one
The sample code of the topic will be used to explain.
Then you don’t have to worry about saying that.
Is it because our midterm exam has different topics?
Then we will all agree to use this one as the basis.
That question
So don't worry if you
Previously taken
What should I do if that topic is different from this one?
You just need this one
Just understand the content
Then I will briefly review our
Midterm exam question 2
What are you taking the exam for?
Then the second question is mainly to ask
Let’s find out what’s inside the data we entered.
The maximum value of
And his sum
Then there is another way to sort the output from small to large.
Mainly these three functions
Then our IO has Clock
Then reset,data in
Then data num
data num is used to tell you about us
How many transactions does the data sequence have?
Then you are going to receive these pieces of information
Then he placed 2-6 strokes
Then this is the result you output
Well, let’s just take a look at the timing diagram:
At the first positive moment after reset
Our data num
There will be a value output
It means we will have several pieces of information next
To receive it, it is in the same cycle
data in will also send the first piece of information
That's because our data num is 2-6
So it’s impossible for you to receive only one payment
The next transaction will begin to be output.
This won't happen
So everyone here just needs to rest assured
Write down your data num
Then connect the first piece of information
Then according to the data num
to receive your information
It's like there are 3 here
Represents next
You have to receive information during the three cycles.
So you receive the first 247 first
The second stroke is 3, the third stroke is 92
Then what's next
The next fourth cycle is here at t3
Then start doing your output
That's what I just said
us
The first output is to output our maximum value
So we have to output 247
Then in the next cycle we will output our sum
That is, the three add up to 342
Then next cycle T5 is here
To start we want
Output our data sequence from small to large
So you have to output three first
Then output 92 in the next cycle
The next cycle outputs 247
Then the next cycle
There will be a new piece of data
Sequence comes in
So you have to receive your data again
That's the same as data in
Then keep repeating this until the simulation ends
You can complete the second question
Then below is his state machine
As you can see, it is at the beginning
Accept the data here and cycle around the data num
Then go to output max and output sum
Then these two states are a cycle
Then you have to go from small to large
output so it takes
data num's cycle
Then go back to your receive data state later
Okay, let me talk about the program part next.
Sorry, only the word pad can be opened
Just make do with it
Is there anything at this size that my classmates can’t see?
I can’t see my classmates raising their hands to let me know
Okay? Let’s start explaining this program.
That
The first thing is to let our IO have clock, reset, data num
data in and result
Then what's next
first
We will need to declare our state
That's because you have 4 states
That’s what we use 2bit to declare.
That
And again, because we need to save the data
Do the output in that sorted state?
We have declared an array here
This is the value_array variable
This register
That’s because we have at most 6 transactions
So here we open 0 colon 5
That's it for sure
We can save all the data we entered.
will not exceed
And then in addition we because we have to remember to say that I total
How many data are there?
when i sort
And when I was receiving information,
Only then do we know how many cycles it will take in that state.
So we have a data num register here
It is used to record the amount of input data
And then I went to get that
Control the writing of my array
Then there are things like reading
I have declared an array_pointer here
used to record
Tell me which array I want to operate now
Location
Then come again because we want to record max
So we also use a register here
To record the maximum value of the current input data
Then sum is used to add up and say that we are now
The sum of input data
Then the result
It’s because we operate in the always block
So we declare reg here
The state part is all 4 states, read data
Then output Max
Output sum and output sorting results
4 states
Then here we use that teacher
The one who taught
How to write combination and sequence separately
so see us
sequentia here
Our state machine is to convert the current state
Less than or equal to Read data
During reset
If the reset is not over, then
We are curence date less than or equal to next state
Then this next state
It will be determined by our combination circuit
That in
When reading the state of data, our next state
It depends on your array pointer
Have you already counted?
data num reg record number
For example, in our example just now
Our data num is 3
Then we will store the number 3 in data num
register
Then our array pointer will count from 123
When counting to the same amount
We can just jump to the next state
output_max
If you haven't counted yet
At that time we will just stay in Read data
Continue to read data
Okay, then go to output Max and it will be a cycle.
So our next state directly gives the output sum
Then the output sum is also a cycle
So our next state is for the next one
output sort
Then in the end it’s the same as output sort
We need to count until the cycle of data num reg
We will jump back to read data state
Otherwise, we will all stay in the output sort state.
Then the above is our state machine
Some students are interested in this part
Don’t you understand? Do you need to explain it again?
Okay? Then I'll move on.
Then it’s us
The main part of data operation processing
Then here we use sequential to write
Then when you first see reset
We'll put ours first
The value array is initialized to 255
The reason why it should be initialized to 255 is because
We want those that have no values ​​filled in
array
Later, when I queued up, I was placed at the end of the queue.
Then we will only output
Suppose our data num is 3
We will only output three transactions
The values ​​of the three arrays of 456 will not be output.
That's because we grew up from small to large
You said you initialized it to 255 at first
The array of values ​​that have not been updated
Rui will automatically be ranked on the side of 456
OK, then data num
Here we initialize it to 7
In fact, how much is this initialized to?
It shouldn't affect anything
Then the arraay pointer is initialized to 0
sum, max, result are all initialized to 0
Then go to our state machine
Part
It is our data num reg when reading data
I have to give value
Then this judgment is because of our TB
After reading your information,
It is our data num after t1
Yes will become 0
So if your data num is 0
It means it has passed t1 now.
So you only have it at t1
You can change your
data num reg value
Otherwise, you will receive the wrong value
So unless you are currently in t1
That is, when data num is not equal to 0
You need to set the value of your data num reg
Then why is it not set to data num here?
But data num - 1 is because
Although I just said our
pointer may be 123
Count to 3
data num is the same
But because our actual circuit operation will
Slightly more
Our index of 0 is not used.
So here we are actually
Put data num - 1 to let him
When I count, I count like 012
Then our data pointer is also 012
This saves resources
Okay, what if the value cannot be changed?
That is, when it is not t1
My Data num Reg
The value is just to maintain its original value.
Then this is the part of Data num Reg
Then there is the array pointer
He is if he hasn’t counted Data num Reg yet
I'll go add one
Then if he seems to be equal to
Data num Reg
The representative said that I have to jump to the next state.
Then we have him here at this time
Make a zeroing movement
Because behind us
When we sort the output, I must start from
array0 array1 array2 starts output
So here I am
Here we are going to do zeroing now
But actually you are in that output max
Or when output sum
You can also do a zero reset
oh
Then the next part is where we have to calculate the sum.
Then everything is very simple here
As long as we all have sum = sum + data_in
That's just a classmate
Remember that you have finished outputting later
Before you go back to read data, you need to reset the sum to zero.
When it was executed for the first time, because we
I already gave him 0 when I reset.
So there will be no problem
But after you read a round of data,
Well, you need to go back to read data.
Remember to do the zeroing action on him
Okay, then this is the max part
So here we are
Because it has been initialized to 0 before
So any data you enter
It must be greater than or equal to them
So as long as you show up
After inputting data in greater than Max
Let’s take Max’s register
The value becomes the data you enter now in
behind that
The second piece of data you want to enter must be larger than this Max
He has to be older before he updates his value.
Then use this method
we can put
You enter the maximum value in the data and record it.
The last part is the sorting part
Then I just talked about our value array
We started by defaulting it to 255
It’s the maximum value of our 8 bits
So you now enter data
We just have to go find him and tell him that he wants to put it in
which position
Suppose you now have data in
It’s smaller than our value array0
Let's come in one at a time
So under such conditions
We are going to find
Now this data
Just wherever he wants to insert it
That
Our original array is already sorted
OK
Then you have to say it now in the first cycle
For example, my
247 input comes in
At this time, all my value arrays are 255
So I'll go here first 255
Among these six arrays
Find a place where 247 can be inserted
Then if I find that it is larger than value array
0 is even smaller
Then I entered this data first
He is the youngest.
Then he should be penetrated
The position of value array 0
So I update value array 0 to data in
Then my value array 1
It needs to be updated to 0 because it needs to be pushed back one space.
Then I want to store the value of 0
2 to store the value of 1
3 is stored as the value of 2
4 is stored as the value of 3
and so on
Oh, let’s assume that my current data in is
Your array0 is even bigger
Does that mean his position is not 0?
I'll look for his position further back
So I went to see if he was better than
value array1 is even bigger
If it is smaller than value array 1
That means I want to move the position of 1 back
Then put my data in into value array1
Because it is bigger than 0 and smaller than 1
Then he should put it in 1 in the new position
So I update value array 1 to data in
Then all other values ​​are pushed back one space.
I store the value of value array1 into value array 2
The value of value array 2 is stored in value array3
Then and so on
Then if he, I have data in now
It’s bigger than both 0 and 1
Then I will compare with 2
The same thing if he is smaller than 2
His position will become in value array 2
So I put value array2
The value of data in is updated
Then the original value of 2 is pushed to 3 and the value of 3 is pushed to 4.
Then do the same operation later
Keep judging till the end like this
Are there any students here who don’t understand?
Oh, if not, then the last step is to sort here.
What I just said is still in the Read data
That is, every time we enter something
We have to make a judgment
So we are still in the Read data state
Then wait until you enter the information
After the number of pens is equal to your data num
You just jump directly to the next output Max
That's because I use one
That Max register records his value
So just put
As long as the result is less than Max
Then we will jump to output sum in the next cycle
That's the same thing I've already done here
I used register to remember his total.
It means that result is less than or equal to sum
Then the next step is output sort.
At this time, I always have the same result
<= vaule_array[array_pointer] because my
The Value array register is sorted.
So I started from his index 0
Output to data num
Just fine
Then this way
In this way, after the data num cycle is output,
This completes our sorted output.
Then finally here you can see how many there are
Judgmental
Determining whether array pointer is equal to Data num reg
if yes
I will initialize my value array to 255
let me next time
You can continue to sort after reading the data.
So here is a judgment made:
If your array pointer is equal to data num reg
Just set vulue array 0 to 255
Otherwise, keep its original value
The same is true for value array1 if it has been
After the output is finished, I will set it to 255
Otherwise, keep the original value
That sum and max are the same
You have to reset it to zero before going back to read data.
Otherwise, if your max here is not reset to zero,
Your next data in will be affected
Because it stands to reason that your next set of information will be
The first one will definitely be
Do you want to write it down first?
Only then can you compare it with subsequent values.
Then if your max hasn’t reset him to zero
You will keep the Max from the previous group
Then if the data you entered today
It happens to be smaller than him
Then you can't cover it up
will go wrong
The same goes for sum
If your sum is not reset to zero
Then you keep adding later
The first value you add will be wrong
Then overflow may occur
Because our number of bits is fixed
So remember, this is where you need to remember
To do an initialization action
That's probably the formula for the midterm exam.
That's probably it
Does any classmate have any questions?
if
There are students who can’t understand this code, but it’s the same
You can continue to ask
Then you are
You can send it to any teaching assistant you want.
Anyway
That is, we will forward it to that person depending on the situation.
Midterm Exam Teaching Assistant
Then I will continue with homework 4
Okay, then what we need to do in homework 4
The topic is that
Edge-based line average interpolation
It is a program for interpolation
Then you can give me a brief introduction first.
It's because when we store some image data
Maybe to save that cost
We might just keep his
Even numbered rows or odd numbered rows
For example, the picture on the left is called odd-numbered rows.
If it's an even-numbered line, it's called black.
It means he is worthless
But we need to make the image
when displayed
We need to perform a restoration action on him
Let him have both even-numbered rows and odd-numbered rows
Otherwise, if you look at it this way, the visual effect will be very poor.
So we have to do it through some algorithms
Interpolation lets him get the value of his odd rows
You can compile the complete image on the right
Then this time we
This is the algorithm used
The edge-based line average interpolation method
That is, he will do something based on the edges.
Judgment of conditions
to make the interpolation results better
So this block overview is like this
We have two memories
That first one is
Grayscale image memory that stores original grayscale data
Then this memory can only be read.
And he can only read it once
So everyone in
Pay special attention when designing
That is, you must save the value you read out.
Otherwise, I won’t be able to read him anymore.
The second one is result image memory
That means you have to write down the information you completed.
What should be paid special attention to here is that
The values ​​of our odd-numbered rows also need to be written back.
It’s just that you can’t just write about you.
Those interpolated points that have been processed
You are the whole picture
This result image memory must be written back
Then you can also use him
To make a temporary storage function
If you want to save resources
Don’t open so many registers
You can now read out the values ​​of these gray scales
You can just use this to make a temporary save first.
This way, otherwise you can only read it once
If you save everything using that register
The area will be larger
Okay, let me show you the position of the feet.
Just like us, this time it’s a positive edge synchronization circuit
Then the asychronous reset of Active high
The require signal is used
It’s worth using the Grayscale memory.
Then I will explain his timing later.
then in data
Just from Grayscale memory
The value of the image data read out
Then there is the control signal of Result image memory
There is
Just use it to tell him whether you want to read or write.
Then when wen is 0
It means you want to read the Result memory
Then if wen is 1, it means that we only need to write to him.
That addr
That's the one you want to operate
Location of result image memory
That data_wr
It is the value you want to write into the result image memory.
data_rd is read from result image memory
The image value has a done signal at the end
Just when you
already
Make sure you write all correct answers to result image memory
when you do
Once it reaches high TB, verification will begin.
Okay, then let’s talk about this and that edge-based
The algorithm for line interpolation
First, we will test your qualifications and give them to you.
It is a 32*16 picture
Then he only has an odd number of rows
Then we are
Want to make this 32*16
The even rows of the graph are interpolated
After the interpolation is completed, it will become 3.
A result of 32*31
Then let’s take this result
Write to our result image memory
You can complete this question
That
Suppose what we want to interpolate today is this black point
Then we will have the two rows above it
Is the reading from the original test data worth it?
That is, our odd-numbered rows have values.
The blue line has no value
You have to interpolate yourself
So if we interpolate these black spots
We will all use the ABCs in the row above him
and the following column de f
These points make conditional judgments
to decide how I want to do the interpolation
The way to judge is that I will look first
Interpolation in all directions
It is the absolute value of the oblique angle a and f
Interpolation between b and e and interpolation between c and d
Then use this interpolation to determine whether he has
edge cases occur
to do something different
interpolation
So after I get the values ​​​​of these three directions
We have to find its minimum value
The minimum value means that he has the least edge.
Then we use
It is the most difficult to interpolate his values.
causing some damage
So I finished d1
After d2,d3
I just know their minimum value
Then if d1 is the smallest
I just use
a plus f divided by 2 is used as the value of that point when I interpolate
If d2 is the minimum, then add b plus 1 and divide by 2
If D3 is the smallest, add c plus d divided by 2
Okay, but there is one thing we should pay special attention to.
If we are at the interpolation point
If this black spot is on the left or right border
Then he may not have a or d
Or there is no c or f
Like this picture, he uses the left border as an example
So he only has points b c e f for reference.
So at this time we are all
If you are on the left or right border
We always use (b+e)/2
As the interpolation value of this black point
There is no need to make judgments anymore
Then this is how we sing
Let’s talk about it next
The timing part of data input
The first is the reading of the grayscale image memory
You can see that at t1
Here we pull the require signal to high
Then TB will be released at t2 at this time
Start giving you a row value
That is, you only need to raise require once
He will give you one row at a time
So you just have to
Be prepared for you to process the data of this row.
Whether it is stored in register or stored in
memory or do calculations directly
He will only give it to you this once
So after you finish reading, you should be right
This row does the processing you need
Otherwise, if you can’t read the value later, you won’t be able to read it again.
Do the operation
But the other thing is the first few assignments
There may be some students who don’t quite understand.
that is
Are the values ​​​​of our TB given by negative karma?
Like here, I have negative fate for pixel0
The next negative edge is for pixel1
Then why do we all talk about it?
Our circuit needs to be
Zhengyuan does synchronization operations
It's because I have bad luck
Although I have negative fate to give value
but
At this time we can see near the red line
His value is changing
Then pixel0 and pixel1
The values ​​in the middle are still changing.
So its value is relatively unstable at this time.
Then if you do the operation here
Some errors are more likely to occur
So TB gives value on the negative edge
Then we are really suitable to access his data
In fact, in Zhengyuan
You can see that the dotted line on the right edge is facing down.
Its value is very stable pixel0
So at this time I will take his value
is relatively safe
Then the next chance
Can I align this dotted line?
If both the left and right sides are pixel1, it will be very stable.
So although we have TB in negative circumstances,
But please ask all classmates
They are all processing this information in Zhengyuan
Okay, wait till then
After all the data of a row has been entered,
Then pixel31 is entered
Go to t3 again
Then you can raise the require
TB will continue to give you the next row.
Pixel
The other thing is
If you have not finished typing
Just before in_data has finished inputting a row
You raise the require
He will never give you a second row directly.
It's just that he won't remember to say
How many cycles can you pull up here?
I’ll give you a few rows
Rather
When he enters now, you can require after he finishes typing.
Only then will he give you a second row
So students, please pay attention here.
good
Then the next step is the result image memory part
Then we are all here
A pixel will correspond to a position
Then we have a total of 992 pixels to save in
There are 992 in total
Then um
First, let’s take a look at the read mode part
If you want to do reed, you need to put
set to low
Then Addr is given
The position you want
The position you want to read
then in the next
If you have a good relationship, you can get his data
Then pay attention here too, that's how you are
We give addr and wen this opportunity
Later, when there may be negative luck, the data will come out.
But at this time, he is still relatively unstable.
So please
Next chance to read this data
Then here is the reading part
Then if it is written
It's you who raised Wen in Zhengyuan
Then give you the location where you want to write at the same time
Then the data you want to write
Then its value will be written to our
result image memory了
Then this assignment is probably like this
Do any students have questions?
Oh no, then let me tell you again about our time
More specifically, there is a software verification part.
But I want everyone to write
Software code to verify your circuit
Then the syntax we specify is c or C++ or Python
Then there are a few points that I would like to talk about.
The first thing is that we have to meet
When the time comes, the certified assistant will use the software code to
Generate the test data for verification
So it's yours
The path to the input image is fixed to this
./image.jpg
we will read
This picture comes in for verification.
Then the next thing is that your first step is
After you read this image.jpg in,
Convert it to grayscale
After converting to grayscale
Our image data is 32*31
So we need to resize it first.
Width is 32 and high is 31
Then because of us
We share that
The original grayscale data is only
odd rows
So you need to remove the even rows
Let him become 32*16
That's how we get it
That fits our circuit
input
Then the next step is to invite everyone to use it
software to create the one we just talked about
The algorithm of edge baseline average interpolation
Take the 32*16 image you generated yourself
Interpolate to 32*31
Then we will have one of your own
to the input graph
Processed 32*16 data
Then you use software algorithms
Interpolated 32*31 image data
Then these two are one
will be the input to our circuit
This 32*16 is the input of our circuit
So everyone should save it as image.dat
The interpolated 32*31 picture
It's made with our software
Theoretically less error-prone
So we just take that data
as ours
golden.dat
Then these are both
One can let TB be used as input data
then next
golden
It will be compared with the output of your circuit.
Then we can get a soft
Body verification generated data
to test our circuit
The other one is image.dat
There is also the format of golden.dat
I just ask everyone to refer to what the assistant teacher gave me.
Our TB will originally attach a set of image.dat
golden.dat
Then please follow that format.
File format to write
Then if you name it, it will be the main function.
Please name it main.c
Or main.cpp or main.py
If your code
For example, say python
We need to call some special libraries.
That means please write it clearly in readme.txt
Then when the time comes, it will be together with the homework
pay
Only a teaching assistant knows how to run your code
Or you have some special execution method
Just sometimes write it in the readme
I won't have to deal with it specially if I can't run when the time comes.
so
Okay, let’s talk about the distribution part.
First, our functional simulation
This time it’s 40%
Then we have some points to give
That is if your odd rows are right
That's 10 points.
Then this should be simple
That means you read in odd-numbered lines
Just write it to the correct location of the result image memory
You got 10 points.
Then comes the boundary part
Is the left or right border
If you have the correct interpolation, you can get another 10 points.
In the end it was
Not the ones in the middle of the left border and right border
interpolation value of even row
If you write it correctly, use 20 points for a total of 40
What about data level simulation?
We only give points if we are all right.
So if you synthesize it
If the circuit passes all tests
It's like 20 points
As for performance, we still get 20 points.
Then our performance
The standard is yours
The cost of the circuit is related to the simulation time
Just according to this formula
Here is also the number of your synthetic resources.
then multiply that by your longest simulation time
So when you simulate it, please
Don't use that fast
Because we are looking at the longest simulation time
Then the value multiplied by this is your scoring
The smaller the score, the higher it will be sorted.
Then we will tell you to pay it when the time comes.
And he has gate level
Completed homework is sorted and divided as follows:
Then this part is 20
Then finally when we verify the software
The same is 20 points
Then the method we test here is
By then
We will use our own hidden test pictures
Go and enter your software testing program
do processing to turn it into
image.dat and golden.dat
Then use these two strokes
The image.dat generated by the teaching assistant’s picture also has
golden.dat to verify your circuit
Then if you can pass
You can get these 20 points
So, please make sure your circuit is
Don’t write about a specific picture, just don’t
Because we originally had group 1 attached
image.dat and golden.dat
That means please don’t take it personally
A set of data to design your circuit
Otherwise, I might change it when the time comes.
different pictures
You can't pass it
So here's the score
You can't get it
And then there’s the other thing to do, please yourself
After writing the software code, several more sets of data are generated.
Go test it and see if your circuit can pass.
If you can't pass
You can think about whether there is anything in the circuit
Bugs may occur under certain data conditions
Like this and then there is
Because we all have the same name
Name it image.dat, golden.dat
That is all to ask students to be careful not to
The portion originally provided overshadowed
Because in addition to software verification, we
The previous score is mainly
Or based on what we provided at the beginning
The one that verified him
The final part paid is the same
Please give me your information
.v put a folder
.v, .sdo put a folder
And then there is our report
put a folder
Then there is the software code
That is .c/.cpp
Then.py
Those and if you have a readme
Just put it all in one folder
The last four folders are compressed together
Then name it HW4_ID_name.zip
Please follow the format
Just use zip compression
Then please follow the regulations when naming it.
Otherwise, 5 points will be deducted.
Then there is something else to remind you
Just ask everyone to do that
After you compress and upload it, please download it.
Verify again
It’s just that many classmates said
What was not saved to the last version?
It's not like he accidentally sent the wrong message when he passed it up.
Then wait until our revision work
Only when he saw the score did he realize why and what he thought
no the same
It's actually quite difficult for us to deal with this.
So please upload it to
Verify before downloading
Make sure the copy you pass is the one you want to pass on
correct answer
Oh and then in the report file part
I just invite everyone to write in Spec
Just write your functional
Then the gate level is pass or fail
Then fill in the one you use
What are these logic ELEMENTS?
photo memory bits然後9 beat element
And the simulation time of your circuit?
You should also post your flow summerary.
Then everyone will take a look at that
report spec
Just follow what you write and you'll be fine
That is to invite everyone
Fill in all the required information
Then the last thing to note is
Because our circuit score this time will be the same as
It will be related to your simulation time
So this time we open it, you can adjust it
TB cycle and end cycle
That cycle refers to yours
Enter the period of clock
The smaller the cycle
The shorter your clock period is
Then your circuit will run faster.
那end cycle
It means that your circuit simulation can cost up to
several cycles
Then this is you
If your circuit needs to run for a long time
You can adjust it
Bigger
That
The impact of cycle on your simulation time is
Suppose you are now
Your circuit needs to run 1,000 cycles
Then I cycled and it was originally 10
That's 10 ns
Then I end up spending 10 times 1,000
is 10000 ns
So if I set my cycle today to 5
5ns
Then I will also run 1,000 cycles
So I'm 5 times 1,000.
I only need 5,000ns
You can finish running
Then my simulation time will be half of the original time.
So cycle means that everyone can try to watch you
How fast can you run after synthesis?
Then our simulations mainly use synthesized codes.
To verify that performance
then our
The homework limit is May 27
4:59 PM Then invite classmates
Don’t wait until the last minute to upload
Then it said that the network was stuck and no transmission was received.
Just try to upload it as early as possible
so
If he has any questions, he can send them to this teaching assistant's mailbox.
If you want to come to the lab to ask questions, you can send an email first.
Make an appointment with this assistant
See if he has time to do this
Then if there are no problems, get out of class can be over.
thank you all